<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Ellen Lee</title>
    <link>https://ellenle3.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ellen Lee</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Ellen Lee (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 16:21:55 -1000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ellenle3.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Seven arcsecond seeing</title>
      <link>https://ellenle3.github.io/blog/20250723_7as/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 16:21:55 -1000</pubDate><author>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</author>
      <guid>https://ellenle3.github.io/blog/20250723_7as/</guid>
      <description>We just came out of an observing run with the IRTF ASM. The weather&amp;hellip; wasn&amp;rsquo;t great&amp;hellip; but we were able to obtain useful data. One night Subaru reported 7&amp;quot; seeing.&#xA;Our 12x12 Shack-Hartmann wavefront sensor looked like wind blowing through a field of wheat. For reference, the subapertures are 4.5&amp;quot; across and the spots usually look like this: I would share focal plane data but on-target images look more like flat fields.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We just came out of an observing run with the IRTF ASM. The weather&hellip; wasn&rsquo;t great&hellip;
but we were able to obtain useful data. One night Subaru reported <strong>7&quot;</strong> seeing.</p>
<p>Our 12x12 Shack-Hartmann wavefront sensor looked like wind blowing through a
field of wheat.
<img alt="12x12 grid superimposed on what should be a grid of spots but instead looks like a coral reef" src="/blog/20250723/12x12horrible.png"></p>
<p>For reference, the subapertures are 4.5&quot; across and the spots usually look like
this:
<img alt="12x12 grid with an image of the star in each subaperture, each of which looks like nice, small point" src="/blog/20250723/12x12spots.png"></p>
<p>I would share focal plane data but on-target images look more like flat fields.
Some conditions are so miserable that they wrap around to being spectacular!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First light of IRTF&#39;s adaptive secondary mirror</title>
      <link>https://ellenle3.github.io/blog/20240428_first_light/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:52:41 -1000</pubDate><author>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</author>
      <guid>https://ellenle3.github.io/blog/20240428_first_light/</guid>
      <description>We successfully completed our first engineering run with IRTF-ASM-1 on Friday. This marks a number of milestones:&#xA;IRTF achieved stable diffraction-limited image quality for the first time. IRTF-ASM-1 is the first adaptive secondary mirror on Maunakea. This is the first on-sky demonstration of the hybrid-variable reluctance actuator technology developed by TNO. Overall, the run went exceptionally well despite the highly compressed timeline of this project. We obtained closed-loop, diffraction-limited images (Strehl ~ 40% in H-band over 5 minutes of integration) and successfully ran the system under a variety of seeing conditions (0.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We successfully completed our first engineering run with IRTF-ASM-1 on Friday.
This marks a number of milestones:</p>
<ul>
<li>IRTF achieved stable diffraction-limited image quality for the first time.</li>
<li>IRTF-ASM-1 is the first adaptive secondary mirror on Maunakea.</li>
<li>This is the first on-sky demonstration of the hybrid-variable reluctance actuator
technology developed by TNO.</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, the
run went exceptionally well despite <a href="/blog/20240428/Mikroniek-2024.pdf">the highly compressed timeline</a>
of this project. We obtained closed-loop, diffraction-limited images (Strehl ~ 40%
in H-band over 5 minutes of integration) and successfully ran the system under a
variety of seeing conditions (0.4&quot; to 0.9&quot;). The first light image was acquired
on <a href="https://blog.bishopmuseum.org/history/hokulea/">Hokule&rsquo;a</a>, which is a tradition
at IRTF.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p align="center">
  <img src="/blog/20240428/hokulea_irtf-1.jpg" alt="snapshot closed loop on Hokule'a"/>
</p>
<p>We had a great team of people all around, including our collaborators at TNO, UCSC,
and IRTF staff. Special thanks in no particular order:</p>
<ul>
<li>IRTF day crew: Paul, Keith, Dwight, Jun, and Darryl supported major work at the
telescope for several months and on short notice.</li>
<li>Our director: John has been very generous with observing time and funding for
the ASM and has been working to balance that with IRTF science.</li>
<li>Telescope operators and assistants: Brian, Bernie, and Frankie supported our
observations the three nights.</li>
<li>TNO: Fred and Saunder took a long flight from the Netherlands to document this
process for National Geographic. Max also joined remotely to help debug the controllers.</li>
<li>Olivier flew in from France to support the first two runs and has helped us
with lab testing as well.</li>
<li>IfA Hilo: Suzanne, Mike, and Mark have kept me sane in the lab.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="group photo in front of IRTF after first light of IRTF-ASM-1; credit: Fred Kamphues" src="/blog/20240428/FKamphues_group.jpg"></p>
<p>The run started on the morning of April 23. The day crew performed a top end
exchange to put the ASM on the telescope. We closed the loop around 2 AM on the
first night after dealing with alignment issues, and the RTC fighting the facility
guider. The run ended on April 26 after three full, productive nights at the
telescope.</p>
<p>We have a ton of data to analyze over the coming weeks, both for presenting basic
on-sky functionality at SPIE and FELIX-like (fast low-order + slow high-order)
correction for my dissertation. Not bad considering that we recieved the ASM from
TNO in mid-February! It&rsquo;s hard to believe that that things went so smoothly given
all of the problems that even mature adaptive optics systems tend to have, let
alone a new technology.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> Because we were worried about flexure, we also got away
with disassembling and reconfiguring the entire wavefront sensor breadboard ~2
weeks before the run began&hellip; The past few weeks have felt like months to me.</p>
<p>Last but certainly not least, the weather was cooperative. The sky was clear
throughout the run. As we were leaving the summit after our last night at IRTF,
we could see cirrus clouds starting to come over the horizon. Talk about good
luck!</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Definitely not a coincidence and totally planned on my part. Hokule&rsquo;a (known
to most in the West as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcturus">Arcturus</a> or
<a href="http://simbad.cds.unistra.fr/simbad/sim-id?Ident=alf+boo">α Boo</a>) is a
prime first light target because it&rsquo;s <em>very</em> bright and goes through zenith at
Hawai&rsquo;i&rsquo;s latitude. The same reasons make it important for Polynesian navigation.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Lots of firsts this run. The response of the ASM is somewhat slow due to the
thickness of the facesheet. The seeing makes it difficult create interaction matrices
on-sky by poking individual actuators and we don&rsquo;t have an intermediate focal plane
to work with at IRTF. Olivier came up with a new method to generate interaction
matrices by sinusoidally modulating the actuators. This method (CACOFONI) will be
described in an upcoming paper.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
