<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Ellen Lee</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/pages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Ellen Lee</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</webMaster>
    <copyright>Ellen Lee (CC BY 4.0)</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pages/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pages/research/</guid>
      <description>Currently, I work with Mike Connelley as an RA for the NASA Infrared Telescope Facility (IRTF) to support the facilitization of a new type of adaptive secondary mirror (ASM). I also split my time as an RA for Mark Chun to investigate the long-term behavior of the ASM and investigate methods of controlling mechanical resonances on large deformable mirrors. Finally, I perform observations of protoplanetary disks with SCExAO to study star and planet formation from its earliest stages.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Currently, I work with Mike Connelley as an RA for the NASA Infrared Telescope
Facility (IRTF) to support the facilitization of a new type of adaptive secondary
mirror (ASM). I also split my time as an RA for Mark Chun to investigate the long-term
behavior of the ASM and investigate methods of controlling mechanical resonances
on large deformable mirrors. Finally, I perform observations of protoplanetary
disks with SCExAO to study star and planet formation from its earliest stages.</p>
<h2 id="a-new-type-of-adaptive-secondary-mirror-for-irtf">A new type of adaptive secondary mirror for IRTF</h2>
<p>My current position is as an RA for IRTF to support the adaptive secondary
mirror and low-order wavefront sensor FELIX, which will allow us to investigate
gains to the performance of our science instruments with active optics correction.
As part of my dissertation, I will investigate the long-term behavior of these
actuators in a telescope environment and control of mechanical resonances</p>
<p align="center">
  <img src="/research/irtf-1.jpg" alt="IRTF-ASM-1"/>
</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06444">my SPIE paper</a></li>
<li>Suz&rsquo;s close loop paper</li>
<li>Arjo&rsquo;s paper
I am also working to facilitize IRTF&rsquo;s adaptive secondary mirror (ASM) with the off-axis facility guider FELIX.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="disk-imaging">Disk imaging</h2>
<p>SCExAO NIR WFS</p>
<h2 id="other-projects">Other Projects</h2>
<h3 id="misc-irtf-instrumentation">Misc. IRTF instrumentation</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m an RA for IRTF</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://irtfweb.ifa.hawaii.edu/~opihi/">&lsquo;Opihi:</a></li>
<li><a href="http://irtfweb.ifa.hawaii.edu/~spectre/">Spectre:</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I also use IRTF&rsquo;s near-IR spectrographs iSHELL (R~55,000) and SpeX (R~2,500)
to support my disk imaging campaign with SCExAO on Subaru.</p>
<h3 id="near-ir-spectroscopy-of-fu-orionis-objects">Near-IR spectroscopy of FU Orionis objects</h3>
<p>iSHELL</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outreach</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pages/outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pages/outreach/</guid>
      <description>Activities Communicating science to the public is especially important in Hawai&amp;rsquo;i, where we have the enormous privilege of observing from Maunakea. Here are the main activities that I&amp;rsquo;m involved with:&#xA;Maunakea scholars JTTU Astroday Science Olympiad at the University of Hawai&amp;rsquo;i: I was also involved in Science Olympiad as an undergraduate. Other than that, I regularly participate in outreach events around the Big Island.&#xA;Mentoring I&amp;rsquo;ve mentored a few students as well!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="activities">Activities</h2>
<p>Communicating science to the public is especially important in Hawai&rsquo;i, where we
have the enormous privilege of observing from Maunakea. Here are the main activities
that I&rsquo;m involved with:</p>
<ul>
<li>Maunakea scholars</li>
<li>JTTU</li>
<li>Astroday</li>
<li>Science Olympiad at the University of Hawai&rsquo;i: I was also involved in Science
Olympiad as an undergraduate.</li>
</ul>
<p>Other than that, I regularly participate in outreach events around the Big Island.</p>
<h2 id="mentoring">Mentoring</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentored a few students as well!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>potpourri</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pages/potpourri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pages/potpourri/</guid>
      <description>background I (pronouns: she/her) grew up in San Diego County with my wonderful parents and my sibling Mael, who are the most important people to me in the world. I flew six hours to the east and attended Cornell University to earn a B.S. in Engineering Physics. Upon graduating, I went six hours to the west for my Ph.D. and ended up in the middle of the Pacific at IfA Hilo.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">background</h2>
<p>I (pronouns: she/her) grew up in <a href="/other/bonita.jpg">San Diego County</a> with my
<a href="/other/mom.jpg">wonderful</a> <a href="/other/dad.jpg">parents</a> and my sibling <a href="/other/mael.jpg">Mael</a>,
who are the most important people to me in the world. I flew six hours to the east
and attended Cornell University to earn a B.S. in <a href="/other/aep.jpg">Engineering Physics</a>.
Upon graduating, I went six hours to the west for my Ph.D. and ended up in
<a href="/other/suz.jpg">the middle of the Pacific</a> at IfA Hilo.</p>
<h2 id="my-friends">my friends</h2>
<p><img alt="dragons in bookshelf" src="/other/friends.jpg"></p>
<p><a href="../clouds">Awesome atmospheric phenomena</a></p>
<h2 id="ancient-history">ancient history</h2>
<p>As an undergraduate<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, I worked on submm/far-IR instrumentation with Gordon
Stacey. I ended up touching many different projects during the 3 years I had there.
Notably, I worked on optomechanical designs for EoR-Spec, HIRMES, and ZEUS-2.</p>
<p>I also had a brief stint working at NASA GSFC. The summer before I advanced
to candidacy, I worked with Terra Hardwick in the Mars Sample Return (MSR)
Capture, Containment and Return System (CCRS) Vision System (VS) lab
(phew&hellip; NASA sure loves complicated acronyms). I created a software
package that automatically preprocesses image data generated with FRED
and trains a convolutional neural network to perform orientation checks
of the orbiting Mars samples.</p>
<p>I feel very fortunate to have worked with kind people at the earliest stages of
my academic career. Thanks for everything, everyone! &lt;3</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I technically started even earlier than this.
When I was in high school, I volunteered UCSD for a few weeks to fabricate
lenslet arrays for POLARBEAR-2. I didn&rsquo;t know anything about instrumenation
at the time, let alone that I would end up in this field albeit
at shorter wavelengths!&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>the atmosphere</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pages/clouds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ellenlee@hawaii.edu (Ellen Lee)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pages/clouds/</guid>
      <description>the atmosphere Check out the Maunakea Weather Center. They have webcams of the summit and interesting meterological information in their forecasts.&#xA;lenticular clouds Have you ever been in 70 mph winds at 14,000 ft above sea level? (Please say &amp;ldquo;no.&amp;rdquo;) It&amp;rsquo;s pretty dangerous, especially if there&amp;rsquo;s ice on the road.&#xA;Here are some cool ones above Hilo&#xA;nice inversion layer When the clouds are low and flat like this, it means that seeing is probably going to be good.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-atmosphere">the atmosphere</h1>
<p><a href="http://mkwc.ifa.hawaii.edu/">Check out the Maunakea Weather Center.</a> They have
webcams of the summit and interesting meterological information in their forecasts.</p>
<h2 id="lenticular-clouds">lenticular clouds</h2>
<p>Have you ever been in 70 mph winds at 14,000 ft above sea level? (Please say &ldquo;no.&rdquo;)
It&rsquo;s pretty dangerous, especially if there&rsquo;s ice on the road.</p>
<p><img alt="lenticular clouds above Saddle Road" src="/atmosphere/lenticular-5.jpeg"></p>
<p>Here are some cool ones above Hilo</p>
<p><img alt="lenticular clouds above IfA Hilo" src="/atmosphere/lenticular-1.jpeg">
<img alt="more lenticular clouds above IfA Hilo" src="/atmosphere/lenticular-3.jpeg"></p>
<h2 id="nice-inversion-layer">nice inversion layer</h2>
<p>When the clouds are low and flat like this, it means that seeing is probably going
to be good.
<img alt="Layer of clouds below Maunakea" src="/atmosphere/clouds_maunakea-2.jpeg">
The image below certainly looks more interesting, but it&rsquo;s likely that there
is more atmospheric turbulence.</p>
<h2 id="atmospheric-optics">atmospheric optics</h2>
<p>22 degree haloes
<img alt="22 degree halo above San Diego" src="/atmosphere/halo-1.jpeg">
<img alt="22 degree Moon halo at Hale Pohaku" src="/atmosphere/halo-2.jpeg"></p>
<p>Sun dog
<img alt="Sun dogs in San Diego" src="/atmosphere/halo-3.jpeg"></p>
<h2 id="i-have-no-idea-whats-going-on-here-but-it-looks-great">I have no idea what&rsquo;s going on here but it looks great</h2>
<p><img alt="clouds near my family home" src="/atmosphere/bonita-2.jpeg"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
